Guide to the Livingston Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Curran and Mulford Family Papers, 1770-1966; Series XI; 11; (28 boxes) + 2 broadside folders
  Eliza Phillips Mulford Curran was the daughter of James H. Mulford and his second wife Mary Moore Cunningham. Known personally and professionally as Lilla, she was born in New York City and attended boarding schools run by noted educators Louisa Barber in Brattleboro, Vermont (1862-1863), and Mrs. Sylvanus G. Reed in New York City (1867-1868); the school year 1863-1864 was spent in Washington, D.C. Lilla Mulford's paternal family was based in New Haven, Connecticut, and she regularly visited there to see her relatives by marriage, the Parker, Robinson, Stone, Townsend, and Trowbridge families, in and around the city. It was in New Haven that she met John Elliott Curran, a student at Yale College. Their courtship began in 1869, and the couple was married in New York on May 27, 1875. In the late 1870s they moved to a home on East Hamilton Avenue in Englewood, New Jersey, where they raised their three children Henry Hastings (1877-1966), Gerald (Jay) Mulford (1879-1960), and Mary Eleanor (1884-1969; married Henry H. Livingston). A devout Episcopalian, Lilla Curran wrote essays and stories for the weeklies Young Christian Soldier, Christian Union, and The Churchman, in addition to features for Harper's Weekly, Demorest's Family Magazine, and the Englewood Press, where she served as literature editor. Under the pseudonym Dane Conyngham, Curran published short stories and a novel, Eunice Quince, A New England Romance (New York, Lovell, Coryell & Company, 1895). She also taught music classes, held and organized recitals, and gave talks on the history of music. After her husband's death in 1890, Lilla Curran remained in Englewood but eventually returned to live in New York City, where she died on September 23, 1936; she was buried with her maternal ancestors in Mount Auburn Cemetery, Cambridge, Massachusetts.
  Henry H. Curran (1877–1966)
  Henry Hastings Curran was born in New York on November 8, 1877, the son of John E. and Eliza Mulford Curran; he was named for an uncle who had died in the Civil War. Curran was raised in Englewood, New Jersey, and graduated from Yale University (1898). He worked as a reporter at the Englewood Times, and as a reporter and editor at the New York Tribune from 1896 (summer vacations) to 1902 where, for many years, he wrote the paper's "Fresh Air Fund" stories. While with the Tribune Curran attended New York Law School, received an L.L.B. in 1900, and practiced in New York before embarking on a half-century career in public service in the city of New York. He worked in all three branches of government, executive, legislative, and judicial, with elected and appointed positions including alderman and chair of the Board of Aldermen (1911-1917), Manhattan borough president (1920-1921), Commissioner of Immigration for the Port of New York at Ellis Island (1923-1926), counsel to City Club of New York (1926-1928), executive head of the Association Against the Prohibition Amendment (1928-1932), director of the National Economy League (1932-1936), city magistrate (1936-1937), deputy mayor under Fiorello H. La Guardia (1937-1939), chief magistrate (1939-1945), and judge in the New York Court of Special Sessions from 1945 until he took mandatory retirement (age 70) in 1947. He ran unsuccessfully for Congress in 1909 and for mayor of New York in 1921, but had served as acting mayor of the city several times while chair of the Board of Aldermen. Curran's commitment to public service encompassed military service as well: he was recruited to the United States Army's Officers Training Camp (O.T.C.) in Plattsburg, New York, in 1915, and won a commission as a major in the Calvary. Assigned to the 302nd Ammunition Train, he was detached with the 77th Division to base camps in Flanders and Bordeaux, and participated in military engagements in other areas of France. Taken ill while there, he was hospitalized for a time in Nice, and returned to the United States in March 1919.
  As he had followed his father into law, Henry Curran emulated both his parents in his literary pursuits, beginning in 1894 when his article "Duck Hawks on the Palisades" was published in Forest and Stream. Thereafter he regularly wrote a columns, editorials, and essays for newspapers and periodicals, and fully understood the power of the media, including radio, which he regularly marshaled on behalf of his career and causes. His writings reveal his special interest in the underprivileged, children, public parks, animals, and stories of the human condition, particularly demonstrated in his writings on immigration (1924-1926) which appeared in popular periodicals including Ladies' Home Journal, Country Gentleman, Colliers, Saturday Evening Post, and fraternal organs including those issued by the Elks and the Masons. Curran published three books with Scribners, Van Tassel and Big Bill (1923), John Citizen's Job (1924), Magistrates Court (1940), and an autobiography, Pillar to Post (1941). A fourth work, "All Sorts and Conditions," an anthology of his "Topics of the Times" columns for the New York Times, short stories, and essays, published and unpublished, dating from 1934 to 1950, was organized but never published. Henry Curran married Frances (Fanny) Ford Hardy (1881-1971) in Seattle, Washington, on October 12, 1905; the couple made their home in the Washington Square neighborhood of Greenwich Village, and had no children. Henry Curran died in New York on April 8, 1966, was buried with his maternal ancestors in Mount Auburn Cemetery, Cambridge, Massachusetts.
  James H. Mulford (1802–1885)
  James Hervey Mulford, a cotton buyer, was born and raised in New Haven, Connecticut; his paternal ancestors had emigrated from England to Easthampton, New York, in the seventeenth century and to Connecticut in the eighteenth century. He married twice, first in 1826 to Rebekah Gorham Atwater (died May 17, 1843), with whom he had four children: Hervey (1827-1866); Mary (1829-1898; married James Henry Coghill); Elizabeth (1831-1879; married Charles W. Crosby); and James Hervey (1836-1885). His second marriage was in 1849 to Mary Moore Cunningham Porter (1810-1897) of Boston, the widow of Horace Porter. Two daughters, Emma (1851-1851) and Eliza Phillips (1852-1936), were born to the couple. The Mulfords primarily lived in New York City but resided for periods in Memphis, Tennessee, and Washington, D.C. Mulford was buried in New Haven's Grove Street Cemetery with his parents, first wife, and son.
  The Curran Family Papers subseries is largely composed of family photographs, but also holds Mary Curran's bible (with family history annotations) and material related to the American Civil War through Henry Hastings Curran's papers.
  The John Elliott Curran Papers subseries contains some personal correspondence, but also holds a number of case files from his brief law career. His Personal Papers hold some school books and drawings, in addition to material he acquired while touring Europe after his college graduation (1870): a collection of French prints and Italian drawings, and a deluxe photograph album containing scenes of Rome. The subseries closes with photographs of Curran and the Yale College campus, and a group of his literary writings, including two copies of his published novel, and a number of his manuscripts. In the latter is his memoir of traveling to the Wilderness battlefield in Virginia to try to find the body of his brother Henry. Curran's Yale class photograph album is at Manuscripts and Archives in Sterling Memorial Library.
  The Eliza (Lilla) Mulford Curran Papers subseries contains correspondence, personal papers, photographs, and writings. There are over one hundred letters that she received from her parents while she was away at boarding school, as well as quantities of letters received from her sisters, cousins, aunts, and friends, writing from their homes and summer resorts in the American northeast; also there are several folders of courtship letters from her husband-to-be, some of which comment on Eliza's talent as a writer. Curran was photographed often during her lifetime, so the subseries holds a wide selection of images of her (and her friends and home in Englewood) in a variety of formats. Writings holds manuscripts and typescripts of short stories and talks on music history, and a memoir titled "Washington, 1863-1864," which recounts her childhood experiences living in that city and meeting Abraham Lincoln at the White House. Tearsheets primarily contains short stories published in the religious weeklies Churchman, Christian Union, and Young Christian Soldier. Curran was also a postcard collector, and her subseries holds an album and a box of loose cards collected during her European and American travels.
  The Henry H. Curran Papers subseries holds personal and professional correspondence, photographs, military records, and a wide selection of Curran's published and unpublished essays; the material is arranged under five headings: Correspondence, Personal Papers, Photographs, Professional Papers, and Writings. Half of the papers document Curran's political career, civic engagements, and private passions, including New York City and his Greenwich Village neighborhood. They are filed in chronological order by the elected and appointed positions he held. Writings include the columns Curran wrote for the New York Times and the Villager, as well as his writings on immigration issues and short stories for popular magazines between 1923 and 1950.
  The Mulford Family Papers subseries primarily contains material related to James H. Mulford and his ancestors, siblings, second wife, and children (with the exception of his daughter Eliza (Lilla) Mulford Curran, whose papers are listed separately in the third subseries). It includes some business and financial papers and correspondence documenting James H. Mulford's career as a cotton buyer, with many portrait photographs of the family. Also of interest in the subseries are two examples of engraved plates for printing family members' visiting cards (still with their advertising wrappers), and James H. Mulford's single literary piece: a meditation on the death of his youngest brother George, from consumption in 1843.
  - Curran family papers
    - Holy Bible (New York: American Bible Society), with manuscript family record (1866-1905) between Old and New testaments, 1864
      Volume presented to Mary Langford Curran, Christmas 1866; photocopies of genealogical annotations are in folder 764
    - Curran and Langford genealogical information, with obituaries, 1877-1943, undated (Box 91, Folder 764)
    - Curran children: group portrait photograph, undated
    - Curran, Edward, 1886, 1894 (Box 91, Folder 765)
    - Curran, George: portrait photograph, undated (Box 91, Folder 766)
    - Curran, Gerald (Jay) M.: portrait photographs, undated (Box 91, Folder 767)
    - Curran, Henry Hastings (1841-1864)
      - Memorial of Henry Hastings Curran (unbound copies), 1867 (Box 91, Folder 768-769)
      - Portrait photographs and engraving, correspondence, clippings, 1861-1886, undated (Box 91, Folder 770)
      - Schoolbook, Prometheus Bound, 1856, circa 1965 (Box 91, Folder 771)
    - Curran family home, Utica, New York: photograph, undated
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1869-1945
    - Langford family photographs, undated (Box 91, Folder 772)
    - Peck family photographs, undated (Box 91, Folder 773)
  - John Elliott Curran papers
    - Correspondence
      - Curran, Edward and Mary, 1875-1877 (Box 92, Folder 774)
      - Curran, Eliza (Lilla) Mulford, 1873-1887 (Box 92, Folder 775-778)
      - Curran, John E.: letters to mother and Henry, 1864-1865 (Box 92, Folder 779)
    - Law office files
      - Cases representing James H. Mulford, 1873-1878 (Box 92, Folder 780)
      - Other court cases, 1872-1881 (Box 92, Folder 781-786)
      - Other court cases, 1872-1881 (Box 93, Folder 787-790)
      - Other legal documents, 1873-1882, undated (Box 93, Folder 791-794)
      - New York State Bar admission certificates, 1873-1880
    - Personal papers
      - Album: "Roma", [1870] (Box 94)
        Deluxe photograph album with sixty images of Rome, many by Michele Mang & Company; bound by L. Olivieri in gold-stamped, and gold-tooled vellum and leather binding, with hand-painted front cover.
      - Holy Bible (Glasgow: William Collins), with manuscript family record (1863-1884) inside front cover, 1858 (Box 95, Folder 795)
      - Drawing and penmanship copy books, and music book, 1850s (Box 95, Folder 796)
      - Drawings, 1858-1870, undated (Box 95, Folder 797)
        Includes images that Curran copied from French prints in his collection
      - French prints, circa 1816-1824 (Box 95, Folder 798)
        Fifteen engravings by Georges Jacques Gatine after Louis Marie Lanté, from Costumes parisiens: les ouvrières de Paris.
      - French prints, 1817-1820 (Box 95, Folder 799)
        Thirty-six lithographs by Charles-Philibert de Lasteyrie after Hippolyte Lecomte, from Costumes de différentes nations ( Costumes européens ).
      - French prints, 1814-1830
        Four lithographs by Philibert Debucourt after Carle Vernet, representing various uniforms of: French and foreign armies, caricatures (Paris: chez Bance, 1814-1815?); two lithographs by Langlumé after Edmé Jean Pigal, from "Moeurs parisiennes," circa 1830
      - French prints, 1828, undated
        Fourteen lithographs, etchings, and engravings, including several social satires and caricatures of the English and the Spanish, by Engelmann, Morner, Bellangé, Delpech, and Vernet, among others; several published by Gihaut freres
      - Italian drawings, undated
        Seventy-four sketches (inlaid on forty-two sheets) by Francesco Maggiotto (1750-1805) in one portfolio
      - Italian drawings, undated (Box 95, Folder 800)
        Two drawings of horses by Giovanni Domenico Tiepolo (1727-1804)
      - Miscellaneous prints, undated (Box 95, Folder 801)
        One etching by Paul Troger, and one unsigned
      - Obituaries, 1890 May
        Includes journals such as Harper's Weekly, Forest and Stream, and newspapers published in New York and New Jersey
      - Scrapbook, 1888-1889 (Box 95, Folder 802-805)
        For additional material, see: Box 150, folder 1190
        Volume established to hold ephemera and clippings related to his novel Miss Frances Merley (1888), but also includes fan mail and clippings of his unsigned published theatrical and literary criticism
      - Miscellaneous papers, 1862-1889 (Box 95, Folder 806-807)
        Includes a humorous letter to Santa Claus, passport, a Yale student newspaper, Williston Seminary catalogue (1865), The Yale Pot-pourri (1869), a German map and military broadside (1870), a guidebook to Milan cathedral (1870), and Index lectionvm (1862)
    - Photographs
      - Portraits, circa 1860, undated (Box 96, Folder 808-809)
      - Williston Seminary group portrait, circa 1865
      - Yale College campus, circa 1869
    - Writings
      - Miss Frances Merley (Boston: Cupples and Hurd) [2 copies], 1888 (Box 96, Folder 890a)
      - Manuscripts, 1864-1897, undated (Box 96, Folder 810-815)
        Includes short stories, poems, and one play; also a narrative of the 146th New York Regiment's activities, and Curran's journey in 1866 to the Wilderness Battlefield to search for his brother Henry's body
      - Tearsheets, 1887-1890
        See also: Box 95, folders 802-805
  - Eliza (Lilla) Mulford Curran papers
    - Correspondence
      - Aspinwall, Frank B., 1872-1874 (Box 97, Folder 816-817)
      - Aspinwall, Minnie, 1873-1875 (Box 97, Folder 818)
      - Benet, Laura, 1929, undated (Box 97, Folder 819)
      - Brown, Harold, 1909, undated (Box 97, Folder 820)
        Contains a "Charles Dickens" envelope
      - Coghill, Mary Mulford, 1873-1890 (Box 97, Folder 821)
      - Coghill, Sarah (Sade) Adeline, 1873-1876 (Box 97, Folder 822)
      - Crosby, Elizabeth (Libbie) Atwater Mulford, 1867-1878 (Box 97, Folder 823)
      - Cunningham, Hannah Thomas
        See: Box 100, folder 868
      - Curran, Gerald (Jay) M., 1905, undated (Box 97, Folder 824)
      - Curran, Henry H. and Frances (Fanny), 1891-1929, undated (Box 97, Folder 825)
        Includes photographs of WWI activities
      - Curran, John Elliott, 1869-1889, undated (Box 97, Folder 826-829)
      - Curran, John Elliott, 1869-1889, undated (Box 98, Folder 830-835)
      - Curran, Mary Langford, 1877 (Box 98, Folder 836)
      - D., Jeanette A., 1873-1874, undated (Box 98, Folder 837)
      - Emery, Julia Chester and Susan, 1874-1876 (Box 98, Folder 838)
      - Kearney, [Phise], 1873-1877 (Box 98, Folder 839)
      - Livingston, Eleanor Mulford, 1932-1936, undated (Box 98, Folder 840)
      - Livingston, Henry Hopkins and Herman, 1930-1936, undated (Box 98, Folder 841)
      - M., Lizzie, 1870-1911, undated (Box 98, Folder 842)
      - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1935 (Box 98, Folder 843)
      - Moore, Caroline, 1873-1878 (Box 98, Folder 844)
        See also: Box 100, folder 868
      - Mulford, James H., 1863-1874 (Box 98, Folder 845-847)
      - Mulford, James H., 1875-1884 (Box 99, Folder 848-849)
      - Mulford, Mary Moore Cunningham Porter, 1863-1885, undated (Box 99, Folder 850-857)
      - Parker, Eliza (Lillie) Townsend, 1870-1877, undated (Box 100, Folder 858-867)
      - Phillips, Eliza Cunningham
      - Price, Susan Cunningham, 1873-1890 (Box 100, Folder 868)
      - Rogers, Hoffman, 1900-1902 (Box 100, Folder 869)
        Includes drawings and watercolors by Rogers
      - Rogers, Lucy Ferdon, 1874-1877, undated (Box 101, Folder 870)
      - Thrall, Julia M. Stone, 1875-1878 (Box 101, Folder 871)
      - Condolence notes [on death of John E. Curran], 1890 (Box 101, Folder 872)
      - General correspondence, 1798, 1861-1936, undated (Box 101, Folder 873-875)
        Invitation to the Atwater Assembly-room (1798) enclosed in correspondence; another ticket in Box 116, folder 1038
    - Personal papers
      - Aldrich, Donald, 1927-1934 (Box 101, Folder 876)
      - Autograph album, 1859-1868 (Box 101, Folder 877)
      - Autograph fans, 1866-1868 (Box 101, Folder 878)
        Two wood and cloth fans signed by friends in Philadelphia, Washington, and Richfield Springs, New York
      - "Book of fate", undated (Box 101, Folder 879)
      - Composition books (five volumes; four hold class notes), 1867-1872, undated (Box 102, Folder 880-882)
      - Diary, 1918 Mar (Box 102, Folder 883)
      - Feather cloak material, 1893-1936, undated (Box 102, Folder 884-885)
        Contains photographs, correspondence, clippings
      - Genealogical notes, 1930, undated (Box 102, Folder 886)
      - Heritage societies, 1910-1926 (Box 102, Folder 887-888)
      - Knitting, 1921-1922, undated (Box 103, Folder 889)
      - Music instruction and recitals, 1889-1922 (Box 103, Folder 890)
        Includes programs, reviews, teaching certificate, and promotional material
      - Obituaries, 1936 (Box 103, Folder 891)
      - Paderewski, Ignace Jan, 1900-1932, undated (Box 103, Folder 892)
      - European tour memorabilia, 1907 Jun-Sep (Box 103, Folder 893)
      - Twing, A. T. (Alvin Tabor), 1876, undated
      - Miscellaneous papers, 1770-1934, undated (Box 103, Folder 894-900)
        Includes two 18th-century Rhode Island lottery tickets, newspaper clippings, libretti, recipes, ephemera, and two watercolor sketches of England
    - Photographs and postcards
      - Portraits, circa 1865-1930 (Box 104, Folder 901-905)
        Includes images in various formats by Louis Alman, Sarony, Bogardus, Mishkin, DeYoung, Hargrave, and Pach Brothers
      - Group portraits including Lilla Curran, circa 1880 (Box 104, Folder 906)
        All tintypes and gem photographs
      - Friends, undated (Box 104, Folder 907)
      - Gem album (Boston: J.E. Tilton & Co.) with 22 miniature images, circa 1880 (Box 104, Folder 908)
      - Family group portraits, circa 1885 (Box 104, Folder 909)
      - Curran home [103 East Hamilton Ave., Englewood, New Jersey] and local street scene, circa 1885 (Box 104, Folder 910)
      - Curran children, circa 1877-1885 (Box 104, Folder 911)
      - Cemeteries, undated (Box 105, Folder 912)
      - Munich, Prinz Regenten Theater, 1901 (Box 105, Folder 913)
      - Queechy Lake, Canaan, New York, circa 1890-1905 (Box 105, Folder 914-915)
        Includes photograph albums with images of Gideon S. Drowne family and home
      - Salmagundi Club, undated (Box 105, Folder 916)
      - Travel photographs, undated (Box 105, Folder 917)
        See also folder 920
      - Tourist souvenir photographs [commercial], undated (Box 105, Folder 918-919)
      - Miscellaneous photographs, circa 1864, undated (Box 105, Folder 920)
      - Postcard album, 1901 (Box 106)
        Holds cards from England, Belgium, Germany, and Austria, and the Cunard Line's Lucania
      - Postcards, circa 1900-1910 (Box 107)
        Cards [mostly commercial] from Great Britain, France, Italy, Germany, Switzerland, Belgium, the Netherlands, with a few from North America
    - Writings
      - Manuscripts, 1929, 1933, undated (Box 108, Folder 921-928)
      - Research material, 1893-1929 (Box 108, Folder 929-930)
      - Review of Eunice Quince, 1895 Dec (Box 108, Folder 931)
      - Tearsheets and journal issues, 1874-1901, undated (Box 108, Folder 932)
  - Henry H. Curran (1877–1966) papers
    - Correspondence
      - Caswell, Edward C., 1933, 1956 (Box 109, Folder 933)
      - Chater, Harry D., undated (Box 109, Folder 934)
      - Curran family (parents and siblings), 1887-1936 (Box 109, Folder 935)
      - Curran, Frances (Fanny) Hardy, and family, 1902-1918 (Box 109, Folder 936)
        Includes letters to Fanny from Henry
      - Curran, Thomas, 1920, undated (Box 109, Folder 937)
      - Johnson, Tristam and Elizabeth, 1911, undated (Box 109, Folder 938)
      - Kemble, Harry A., 1943-1945 (Box 109, Folder 939)
      - Lindquist, Harry L. and Marion, 1957, undated (Box 109, Folder 940)
        Includes two etchings of New York scenes by Paul Berdanier (1879-1961)
      - Livingston, Herman, 1944 (Box 109, Folder 941)
      - Parsons, Mabel, 1933, 1957 (Box 109, Folder 942)
      - Miscellaneous, 1890-1949 (Box 109, Folder 943)
    - Personal papers and subject files
      - Diaries, 1889, 1891, 1924 (Box 109, Folder 944)
        Two boyhood diaries with one travel diary kept by Frances Curran
      - Century Club, 1947 (Box 109, Folder 945)
      - Church of the Ascension, 1940-1942, undated (Box 109, Folder 946)
      - Ephemera, 1890-1945 (Box 109, Folder 947-948)
        Includes an etching, "Monroe's House," by Edith Nankivell
      - Genealogy notes, undated (Box 109, Folder 949)
      - Ku Klux Klan, 1929, undated (Box 109, Folder 950)
      - Law practice, 1904 (Box 110, Folder 951)
      - Military service papers: World War I, 1915-1919 (Box 110, Folder 952-958)
        Includes correspondence, photographs, postcards, and two Gorham "Pro Patria" medals
      - Obituary, 1966 (Box 110, Folder 959)
      - Sheet music, 1898-1958
      - University Club, 1943 (Box 110, Folder 960)
      - Writings about Henry H. Curran, 1922-1950
      - Yale University, 1896-1957 (Box 110, Folder 961-962)
    - Photographs
      - Curran, Frances (Fanny) Hardy, undated (Box 111, Folder 963)
      - Curran, Henry H.
        - Portraits, circa 1880-1947 (Box 111, Folder 964-967)
          Existence and Location of Originals
          Also stored in: Oversize, Box 153, folders 1214-1217
        - World War I, 1917-1919
        - Yale University and alumni events, undated
      - Unidentified people, undated (Box 111, Folder 968)